<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Loues complaint, for vvant of entertainement A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the third of December, 1609. By William Holbrooke.</title>
            <author>Holbrooke, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13564</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104136</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839875</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839875</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4334</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03443)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4334)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1208:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Loues complaint, for vvant of entertainement A sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the third of December, 1609. By William Holbrooke.</title>
                  <author>Holbrooke, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Windet] for Nathaniel Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1610?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name supplied and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4334:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4334:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LOVES COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLAINT, FOR WANT of Entertainement:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Sermon preached a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> PAVLES CROSSE, <hi>the third of</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, 1609.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM HOLBROOKE.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <head>IW</head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Butter.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4334:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4334:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, Sir <hi>Thomas Cambell,</hi> Knight, and the now Lord Maior of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Citie of LONDON, all true honour, grace and happineſſe be multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough it bee true (Right</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable) which is commonly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that great men haue many eares, and that the eyes of many are vpon the rich, yet I know it to be as true, that they haue as fewe true friends as any, for who more licentious and out of order, and who more incorrigibly and vnreprooued, walke in wickedneſſe then many of them? Let experience ſpeake, and yet either the timerouſnes of their profeſſed friends, or their owne greatnes, keepe ſuch as ſhould, farre from entring into reproofe of them, and ſuch as would, withhold themſelues from it, becauſe moſt commonly both they and their true friendſhip finde hard enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment. I haue therefore Right Honourable,
<pb facs="tcp:4334:3"/> (preſuming vpon your kind acceptation of what I haue done) made bolde to dedicate this little worke vnto you, that you may haue that dayly in your hands and before your eyes, which once ſounded in your eares. The reaſons enſuing I hope will excuſe my boldneſſe, and pleade, yea, preuaile for kind entertainement. For firſt, to whome doth it of right more belong to, then to your ſelfe, both in reſpect of the place where it was preached, your attention and readineſſe in hearing, (eſpecially when you in particular were ſpoken to) and the matter therein contained? which doth as much, if not more, concerne you then any that were hearers there that day, both for the inſtigating of you to diſcountenance ſinne, by ſtopping the ſtreame and courſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny groſſe corruptions in your Citie, which GOD calleth for at your hands, in reſpect of your place, as alſo to the countenancing of good in all wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers. Secondly, we are all through our owne in bred corruption, and the readineſſe of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill to choke good things begun, more ready not to heare, and forget hauing heard, then to heare: remember, and practiſe what is taught, which
<pb facs="tcp:4334:3"/> moueth me by writing to bee a Monitor to your Honour, of that I was by my mouth. Laſtly your kind acceptation of it being heard, as appeared by your ſpeech to me, your profeſſed reſolution to doe what you might (though you could not doe what you would) with your honourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect (as to all Miniſters comming to that place ſo) to me, challengeth this labour onely to your ſelfe. Theſe reaſons conſidered, I hope (right Honourable) this Glaſſe which I dedicate vnto you without all ſiniſter reſpect, (onely ayming at Gods glory therein, your good, and the good of your renowmed Citie,) will not onely bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained of you, but carefully looked on by you from day to day, it will proue one of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt Monitors and ſoundeſt friends about you, it will lye for no cauſe, it will not call white blacke, nor blacke white, it will not be meale mouthed, it will not be bribed by kindneſſe to conceale your errours if you goe awry, nor moued by vnkinde dealing to exclaime of you, and ſay more then is true, or require more then is your due to pay to God, and the place ouer which God hath called you to rule, therefore what more worthy enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement
<pb facs="tcp:4334:4"/> then ſuch a true and truſty Friend? which not doubting of, I will ceaſe from further troubling your Lordſhip with vnneceſſary lines, though not ceaſe to pray for you, that you may ſo walke and proue your ſelfe a man in this your preſent Office, as the iſſue thereof may be to the glory of God, the good of this Citie, and the true peace of your owne Conſcience.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips to bee commanded, <hi>WILLIAM HOLBROOKE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4334:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, what I was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to my expectation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to preach, I haue at the very earnest and importunate requeſt of many, conſented to be publiſhed, therein keeping my ſelfe as neere as I can to the very words I vſed in the preaching of it, without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or detraction, neither affecting curioſitie of words in the one nor the other, but trueth and plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which hath euer proued beſt, and will I hope ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to euery conſcionable Reader to be herein. The captious I regard not; the Pulpit is a place not for a man to ſhewe his wit and reading in, to worke vpon the eare by, but the iudgement; plaineſſe, and euidence of the spirit to wound and worke vpon the conſcience by, which I eſpecially aimed at: what good it hath wrought, I ceaſe to speake more then to God in thankeſgiuing: what good it may worke, let thee and me heartily deſire. Shew thy loue to the trueth by paſſing by (in the reading of it) without rigid
<pb facs="tcp:4334:5"/> cenſure, what ſhall ſeeme harſh vnto thee, (I intended not the pleaſing, but the inſtructing of all therein) Giue thanks to <hi>GOD</hi> for what good is therein reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and helpe me and the Church with the benefite of thy prayers. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the beſt band</hi> William Holbrooke.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4334:5"/>
            <head>LOVES COMPLAINT for want of Entertainment.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. CORINTH. 13.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Loue reioyceth not in iniquitie, but in the trueth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the eyes of the people were fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened vpon our Sauiour (right Honorable, right Worſhipfull, men, fathers and brethren, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt) that they might with the more attention heare what he would ſay; ſo are yours vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, expecting the Subiect I intend to ſtand vpon, to anſwere your expectation: wherein, vnderſtand, that to meddle directly with controuerſies abroad, or amongſt our ſelues, ſo often inculcated vpon and trauailed in, I intend not, leſt I ſhould not ſay more then formerly hath beene ſaid, or trouble your eares with the ſame, though happily by a cunning Cooke it might be ſerued in, in other diſhes; counting it more then folly for a Phyſition, to forſake his patients mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally ſicke at home, and to runne abroad for others; much more folly, yea and madneſſe it ſelfe for mee, a Phyſition of the Soule, to leaue you my auditors ſnor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:4334:6"/> and ſleeping, yea ouerſpread with ſinne, and to buſie my ſelfe in matters afarre off, that nought or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle concerne you. My intent then is at this preſent, to diſcouer vnto you your iniquities, whereof you are mortally ſicke, and that which is worſt of all, you will not bee cured; eſpecially I intend to ſhewe vnto you your want of Loue, by your manifeſt iniuſtice, and want of Reioycing in true and honeſt dealing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion towards God. Which my promiſe that I may make good, I will (both for your helpe of memorie and my better facilitie in ſpeaking) obſerue this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode. 1. Shewe the connexion of this, with that which praecedeth. 2. Declare the ſenſe of the words in retaile and by groſſe. 3. Lay open the parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, into which it doeth diuide it ſelfe: and laſtly, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle the ſeuerall inſtructions thence ariſing.</p>
            <p>For the connexion of it: The Apoſtle in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter next before going, hauing laid downe the ſeuerall functions of men in the Church, in the laſt verſe of the ſame,<note place="margin">Verſ. 28.</note> in concluſion hee exhorteth the Corinthians, and vs in them, to deſire the beſt gifts. Vpon the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring whereof, it ſeemeth ſome did or might conclude, that ſo they would do, for they would ſtriue to ſpeake excellently, and to be men of great knowledge, &amp;c. and what better then theſe? for the better inſtructing of whom, the Apoſtle in the three firſt verſes of this Chapter, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ueth them to vnderſtand, that it is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to haue theſe and the beſt gifts, except they had loue, and accordingly did vſe the ſame: which he am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifieth by laying downe particulars, as firſt, that it is to no ende to ſpeake with the tongue of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and to be without loue, verſ. 1. ſecondly, that it
<pb facs="tcp:4334:6"/> is to as little purpoſe, to haue the gift of prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and that in the largeſt manner and meaſure; yea to haue faith, that is, the gift of doing miracles, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loue: thirdly, it is to no purpoſe for a man to be ſo liberall and kinde hearted, as to giue all they haue to the poore; and laſtly ſo to ſuffer as to be burned, without loue all theſe profite nothing. Vpon this might ſome reply and ſay, Thou doeſt not thinke vs altogether inhumane and void of loue, doeſt thou? Vnto which <hi>Paul</hi> doeth ſecretly reply, You may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue your ſelues in your iudgement, for euery loue is not the loue I ſpeake of and meane here: and that you may not be deceiued, whether your loue be this yea or no, obſerue whether it haue the ſeueral marks and notable effects, I propound vnto your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which charitie (proceeding from iuſtifying faith) hath: and to this ende the Apoſtle from the 4. verſe of this Chapter to the end of the 7. verſe, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth downe a chaine conſiſting of 14. linkes, euery linke whereof is a ſeuerall marke of this true loue: amongſt which this verſe is one: ſo that this verſe conteineth a true marke of loue, by which faith doth worke, beeing the tenth linke of this chaine: And thus you haue the conexion of it.</p>
            <p>The ſenſe of the words, being the ſecond thing I promiſed, is to be conſidered by examining the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall wordes, comparing the tranſlation with the originall, and the acceptation of them elſewhere in holy Writ: For the word <hi>Loue,</hi> it is in vaine to ſtand long vpon the acceptation of it, it being diuerſly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the Scripture, the mind of the Apoſtle being
<pb facs="tcp:4334:7"/> eaſily perceiued, that heere hee meaneth that loue, which he ſpeaketh of elſewhere, ſaying, <hi>Faith,</hi> that is, iuſtifying faith, <hi>worketh by loue:</hi> and elſewhere cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it <hi>the fruit of the ſpirit, Gal. 5.22.</hi> The word tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated <hi>Iniquitie,</hi> is in the originall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is moſt commonly tranſlated <hi>Iniuſtice,</hi> yet in the Scripture hath both a generall and reſtrained ſenſe, generally comprehending all ſinne: and ſo it is taken in that 5. of the firſt of Iohn, ver. 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe is ſinne:</hi> and ſo doeth <hi>Ezra</hi> vſe it in his prayer, Chap. 9. ver. 6. and <hi>Dan. 9. v. 5.</hi> Reſtrainedly it is taken for iniuſtice betwixt man and man, which I take to bee eſpecially meant in this place: ſo you ſhall finde it taken in the laſt of the Reuelation and 11. verſe, <hi>He that is vniuſt, let him be vniuſt ſtill:</hi> and in the 16. of Luke, verſe 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>And the Lord commended the vniuſt ſteward:</hi> or rather according to the originall, the ſteward of iniuſtice: ſo is the ſimple word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> taken for iuſtice, that is, honeſt dealing betwixt man and man. Titus 1.8. ſpeaking of a miniſter, ſaith he, he muſt be righteous, that is iuſt, which the word [holy] following ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. In the ſecond at the 12. verſe, the grace of God teacheth vs that wee ſhould loue, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, righteouſly, that is, iuſtly which the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> following plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſheweth. Now wee ſee the acceptation of this word in the Scripture, the Queſtion is, how it is to be taken in this place, vnto which I Anſwere, though I take the ſecond ſenſe, to be eſpecially meant in this place, yet I ſee no reaſon why it may not carie both the ſenſes here, both which doe ſet out the nature
<pb facs="tcp:4334:7"/> of Loue the better, and therefore I wil take it in both ſenſes (but ſpecially in the latter) it being the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt way to conſtrue Scripture, and take it in the lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt ſenſe, when both the drift of the holy Ghoſt, the ſenſe of the originall words, and the Analogie of Faith, gaineſay it not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[But reioyceth]</hi> The word in the originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth together, which ſome expound, doth requite good dealing with good dealing, which althogh I do not condemn, yet I rather cleaue to this expoſition by way of <hi>Antitheſis</hi> to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that as loue doth not reioice in ſinfull and vniuſt courſes, ſo it reioyceth to ſee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers together with himſelfe, to take delight in iuſt dealing with men, and religion towards God, fully expreſsing the nature of true loue both in hating and diſtaſting of euill, as alſo in the louing of good, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing theſe effects whereſoeuer it is.</p>
            <p>For the word <hi>Trueth,</hi> it is diuerſly taken in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſometimes for the Sonne of God, <hi>Ioh. 14.6. I am the way, the Trueth, and the Life.</hi> Sometimes for the word of God, <hi>Ioh. 17.17. Sanctifie them with thy Word, thy Word is Trueth.</hi> Sometimes for honeſt dealing and true ſpeaking, <hi>Epheſ. 4.25. Speake the trueth euery man to his neighbour:</hi> where, by <hi>Trueth</hi> is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meant to ſpeake as the matter is, but alſo to deale honeſtly. And ſometimes for religion profeſſed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word of God, as in that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs, <hi>Buy the Trueth, but ſell it not.</hi> And <hi>2. Ep. Ioh. ver. 4. I reioyced when I found of thy children walking in the Trueth.</hi> Amongſt the diuers acceptations whereof,
<pb facs="tcp:4334:8"/> I tie my ſelfe to the two later by way of <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering my acceptation of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the former part of the verſe, and thus haue you the ſenſe of it in parcels.</p>
            <p>Now to totalize the ſame, and caſt it vp altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it commeth to thus much, that that perſon in whom true Loue is (by which faith doth worke, and is a fruit of the Spirit, and by which our actions mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured and performed doe pleaſe God), as hee doth not take delight in ſinne and vniuſt dealing, ſo he doth on the other ſide, yea it is his ioy and great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to deale iuſtly with men, and walke religiouſly towards God, in his owne vſe, and to ſee others to doe the ſame; and thus haue I performed the ſecond branch of my promiſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The parts into which this verſe doeth offer it <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſelfe are two; 1. <hi>Quid Charitas abſtinet,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Loue reioyceth not in iniquitie,</hi> that is farre from <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the propertie of true loue: 2. <hi>Quid efficit,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>but reioyceth in the Trueth,</hi> which loue euer doeth. And that is the third branch of my promiſe.</p>
            <p>The fourth remaineth: Let vs haſten thereunto, that wee may ſee how theſe fiue barley loaues and two little fiſhes, will feede ſo many hundreds as you be here gathered together, or this little pitcher of oyle will fill all the veſſels you haue brought, pay you that it oweth you and you expect, and bee able not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding to ſtand of it ſelfe.</p>
            <q>Out of the ſetting downe of this marke, and ſetting in of
<pb facs="tcp:4334:8"/> this linke into this chaine, by the Apoſtle; firſt ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what it doeth not; ſecondly, ſhewing what it doth: wee obſerue this instruction.</q>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> Where there is any fruit of the ſanctifying Spirit of God, there and in that perſon is the abſence of the contrary euill,<note place="margin">Graces pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is ſinnes abſence, ſins abſence is graces pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</note> and where there is a conſcionable ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence from any euill, there is the preſence of the contrary good Which trueth this with other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures will make plaine vnto vs: for the orderly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding wherein, obſerue that this Doctrine hath two parts, and therefore requireth that they be apart handled. The firſt, namely that where there is any true fruit of the ſanctifying Spirit of God, there is an abſence of the contrary euill, the Pſalmiſt directly proueth, in Pſal. 34.4. ſaying, <hi>Eſchew euill, and doe good:</hi> as though he ſhould ſay, euill and good cannot ſtand together, thou muſt auoyde the one before thou canſt doe the other; with whom the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> agreeth, <hi>chap. 1. ver. 16.</hi> where God teaching the delinquent Iewes, what courſe to take to come into his fauour, which they could not doe, continuing in their filthineſſe, and beſet with the dyrt of their ſinnes as they were, aduertiſeth them firſt to waſh and make themſelues cleane from that filthineſſe, ſinne had brought vpon them, and then, (for vntill that was put away, it was to no end) to ſeeke iudgement, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue the oppreſſed, &amp;c. Whereby hee would teach them, that there could be no true compaſsion and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right walking in them, except they were firſt purified, and their ſinnes abandoned, and the very ſelfe ſame doth <hi>Dauid</hi> affirme in the firſt Pſalme, the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb facs="tcp:4334:9"/> verſes, deſcribing a godly man, firſt, from what he doeth not, in the firſt verſe; ſecondly, from what he doeth, in the ſecond verſe; being well acquainted with the courſe of ſanctification, and euery part of <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> the ſame: Namely, that foraſmuch as man is natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet to worke iniquity, there muſt be a depriuation of that before there can be, or truely is, a poſſeſsion of good: a man muſt ceaſe to bee a ſonne of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> who is earth earthly, before he can be a Son of <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> who is heauen heauenly. Of this doeth the Apoſtle likewiſe render a reaſon, ſaying, <hi>What fellowſhip hath Christ with Belial, or light with darkeneſſe?</hi> which ſpeach for our preſent purpoſe, is worth the marking: for before Chriſt take poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of vs, &amp; draw vs to him, we are no better then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, ruled &amp; ſwayed by the deuil the Prince of the aire, with whom, when chriſt commeth into thee, thou cea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſt to haue any further fellowſhip: the preſence of Chriſt is the abſence of him. And againe, by nature we are the children of darkeneſſe, yea, darkeneſſe it it ſelfe. Now when light commeth, that is, the graces of Gods Spirit, the beames of the Sun of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, our darkneſſe vaniſheth away as the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the night, from couering the world before the Sunne; and darkneſſe in particular places and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate roomes before a candle; which plainely conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth my doctrine, that where Chriſt is, the deuill is abſent; in whom Chriſt hath a foote, the deuill hath no pawe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> To examine our ſelues that bragge ſo much of ſanctification, and our plenitude of the graces of
<pb facs="tcp:4334:9"/> Gods Spirit, what our ſtanding is, whether it bee as we take it to be: If it bee, thou art metamorphoſed, there is not that euill was in thee before, neither art thou the man thou waſt. Thou canſt ſay, I was a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemer, but now by the grace of God I am that I am; I was a perſecutor, but now that is farre from me; I labour more to build vp the Church and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it, then all the reſt of the Apoſtles. I was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, but now Chriſt hath caſt his couering ouer me, I went aſtray, but now am returned to the Shepheard &amp; Biſhop of my ſoule. Which not ably meeteth with the meere ciuill honeſt man, that thinketh to come to heauen with his ciuility, bleſsing himſelfe in his cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate, he is as well as can be, hee is not without the graces of Gods Spirit, no that he is not. He hath ſerued God all his life long, hee hath beleeued euer ſince he was borne, he hath had a care to liue honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and pay euery man his owne (although it neuer came into his minde to pay God his due) he ſerueth God after the maner of his countrey, goeth to the Church vpon the Sabboth both to morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning prayer, and when hee can haue leiſure on the worke day, if there be any exerciſe, and when hee can attend, he hath prayers in his familie (which he taketh as a worke of ſupererogation) and what would you haue him to doe more? Alas, alas poore ſoule, thou art led hoodwinkt in the way of perdition, what alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is in thee, what change, from whence do theſe proceede? from the abſence of the contrary euill, then all is well, if not, Know, that where there was neuer any battell, there was neuer any conqueſt; and
<pb facs="tcp:4334:10"/> where there neuer was a depriuation of euill, there neuer was the true entrance of the contrary good. If thou haue true knowledge, ignorance is diſpelled as a cloud, and thruſt out as not worth the keeping: If thou haue true faith, infidelity is driuen away and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned. Wherby we ſee what are the religious and charitable workes of the meere naturall man, in truth nothing but <hi>Candida peccata, Beautifull ſinnes,</hi> becauſe they ariſe not from the abſence of the contrary euill.</p>
            <p>O then, let euery one of vs that brag and boaſt of our ſanctification, or any fruit of the ſpirit, examine and trie our ſelues, when the euill ſpirit went from vs. And thus much for the firſt part of the doctrine: the ſecond followeth, namely:
<q>Conſcionable abstinence from ſinne produceth and bring<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth forth the contrary good.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The fruits of the ſpirit grow where ſinne once did, now conſcionably abſtained from; which <hi>Pauls</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample euidently prooueth: For, whereas hee was a perſecutor and blood ſucker, of the blood of Gods Saints formerly, behold, now hee is a <hi>Paul,</hi> no ſuch fruit groweth on this tree, but the pleaſant fruits of the ſpirit: hee is become of a perſecuter, an earneſt proſecuter of the Goſpel; of a blaſphemer, a bleſſer of all ſuch as goe on in the trueth of Chriſt, formerly by him euill ſpoken of; of a foe, a fortitude to the Church; of a deſtroyer, an infatigable builder vp of the ſame. And truely there is no reaſon why this ſhould ſeeme ſtrange vnto vs: for, if corruption attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vnto vs from the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> doe bring foorth the curſed fruits of vnrighteouſneſſe in euery ſonne of
<pb facs="tcp:4334:10"/> 
               <hi>Adam,</hi> why ſhould not grace, obtained vnto by the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> be fruitful, once entred into the place of the former. Secondly, the Apoſtle plainely affirmeth <hi>That where ſinne abounded, grace aboundeth much more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> This at the firſt looke plainely telleth vs, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ceaſing from ſinne, is not a conſcionable ceaſing therefrom, and that a man may leaue off the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſinne, and go to hell for it when he hath done: for hee did not of conſcience ceaſe from the ſame, there appeares no contrary fruit of the ſpirit: looke to this ye old Adulterers and ancient Bauds, you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable Libertines and Epicures, you now neigh not after your neighbours wiues, and daughters, and maids as formerly; yee now ſpend not the time in eating, drinking, and riſing vp to play as you had wont to doe. Oh now you are in a bleſſed eſtate, ſay you of your ſelues, and others of you: for why? you are much amended; you are not now ſo bad as you were. No God-a-mercie to thee: thou art reſtrained there from, the heat and ſtrength of thy youth is paſt, thy liuing and goods are conſumed, &amp; thou brought to a morſell of bread; and ſo neceſsitie, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience reſtraineth thee, thou haſt as greene thoughts, though gray haires, as any; thou wanteſt no euill, but meanes; thou haſt as inſatiable deſires after meate and drinke as euer, but thou lackeſt power to affect it, alas poore ſoule, thou muſt to hell, except thou of conſcience leaue thy ſinnes, which thou now <hi>nolens volens</hi> art reſtrained from. Looke vnto this you bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy minded olde men who haue liued by quarelling and ſhedding of blood all your dayes, but now are
<pb facs="tcp:4334:11"/> decrepite and impotent, not vnwilling, but haue as <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> good a heart as euer you had to that ſport.</p>
            <p>This letteth vs ſee, that it is not enough if we doe not euill, but we muſt alſo doe good, beating downe to the ground that Maxime of nature, that I thanke God, I doe no man harme, as I can doe him no good; as alſo ſhewing how groſly the Papiſts doe belie vs, and our doctrine of iuſtification by faith, onely to be a doctrine of liberty and licentiouſneſſe, whereas we teach and tell our people, that without both pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of dueties of pietie, and workes of charitie, there is no conſcionable abſtinence from ſinne, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſequently no way but to hell.</p>
            <q>Loue reioyceth not in iniquity:] vnderſtanding the word iniquity for ſinne, according to the generall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of the word, it offereth this Doctrine.</q>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> He that truely loueth himſelfe and others, is farre from taking delight in ſinne, true loue taketh no ioy, it cannot, neither doth it ſolace her ſelfe, nor make her ſelfe merrie with ſinne. For the proſecuting of this doctrine, we muſt vnderſtand that ſinne is either at home or abroad, ours or others; in neither doth Loue reioyce: as witneſſe the example of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> who was farre from taking delight to commit that ſinne of vncleanneſſe; but ſheweth his diſlike to his Miſtriſſe for importuning him thereunto, whereby hee did manifeſt the trueth of his loue to God, his owne ſoule and body, and both fidelity and loue to his Maſter. For the latter, the vexation of righteous <hi>Lot,</hi> and the
<pb facs="tcp:4334:11"/> ſtreames of teares flowing from <hi>Dauids</hi> eyes, the one becauſe of the vncleanneſſe of his people, the other for the tranſgreſsion of his, ſtand vp to witneſſe. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> Which trueth Reaſon will plainely conuince vs of, how ſuch are renewed and made to loue where God doeth, and hate where he doth, and therefore cannot make themſelues merry with ſinne, which God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Hereby as in a glaſſe, that will not deceiue vs, may we looke our ſelues, and ſee whether there bee true loue in vs yea or no, if wee neither make ourſelues merry with our owne ſinnes nor the ſinnes of others, the common ſickeneſſe of our age and people. Firſt for thy ſelfe, let thy reioycing to grieue the hearts of the godly witneſſe thy want of loue. Is it not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and knowen tricke amongſt you, to vaunt what you haue done in vexing the godly, ſaying vnto thy partner in euill in this manner. O Sirrah wote you what and where I haue bene? I was where a Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane one of theſe preciſe fellowes was, that cannot endure an oath, but I ſo ſware, ſtar'd and ſwaggard that I rid him out of the houſe and companie where I was? O miſerable and wretched, thou art enemie to thy ſelfe, reioycing in thy owne fall. Againe, you night walkers, when yee haue found your mates and haue effected your wiſhes: Doe not you returne home, being not aſhamed to boaſt to your mates, what good ſucceſſe you haue had in theſe manly courſes, and how manly, beaſtly I would ſay, you caried your ſelues in the ſame? Thus may you ſee, there is little loue, becauſe reioycing and merrie making at our
<pb facs="tcp:4334:12"/> owne ſinnes, and if we come to examine our ſelues, how we make our ſelues merrie with the ſinnes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we ſhalbe conſtrained to ſay there is no loue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth. Firſt doeſt not thou reioyce at the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe and beaſtlineſſe of thy owne children and ſeruaunts, their wantonneſſe &amp; abominable drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? with blaſphemous ſwearing: what gentleman is there that muſt not crie guiltie vpon this exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation? But howe much more theſe vngracious wretches that wil ſet their ſeruants to ſweare, and cry as a Beare-ward to his Beare, finely ſworne, nay, will lay wagers of one ouerſwearing another, firſt they will begin the price themſelues, and not being able to get the victory, hauing damned their owne ſoules, will ſet one of their Seruing men (whom they know to be moſt graceleſſe) to maintaine it, whileſt he ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by, making himſelfe merry with the bloodie oathes of the contenders? O horrible! and whoſe heart is not aſtonied to heare this? and is not the like both abroad and at home more then rife by drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Pitifull to behold, and grieuous to ſpeake of. Looke vnto theſe things beloued, and the Lord giue you vnderſtanding, know if theſe things be ſo, there is no true loue in you.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> A man hath none that hateth him more then he doeth himſelfe, vntill hee can lament and mourne for his ſinne, ſmite himſelfe vpon his thigh, and be aſhamed, yea, confounded of his owne wicked wayes.</q>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> This teacheth vs who loue vs moſt, not they that
<pb facs="tcp:4334:12"/> will flatter vs, and ſay, All is well done, but thoſe that moſt deny to yeeld vnto vs in our ſinfull courſes, that are ſad and heauy when we ſinne, that can mourne and weepe when we reioyce in our iniquitie. O con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this, ye that are Gentlemen and haue many ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, thoſe loue thee moſt and without diſsimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that will not foſter thee in thy ſinne, but ſhewe diſlike to the ſame.</p>
            <p>Here we may ſee the difference betweene nature <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>4</label> and grace; the naturall and the ſpirituall man; the former is proud of ſinne, and reioyceth in iniquitie; the latter is farre from it, taketh no pleaſure in it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it and oppoſeth himſelfe againſt ſinne. Doeſt not thou reioyce in ſinne, but art vnwillingly haled and pulled thereto? happie art thou, is it not ſweete vnto thee afterward, but grieuous, &amp; a burthen preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thee downe? thou art truely ſpirituall.</p>
            <q>Motiues to mooue vs to be farre from reioyccing in our owne or others ſinnes.</q>
            <p>Firſt conſider the ende of euery ſinne whoſeſoeuer it is, without repentance, damnation: ſo that a man is going to the place of execution when hee commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſinne, let this conſideration enter into thy heart, and it will make thee farre from being merry at ſinne, wilt thou grieue to ſee a man to goe from Newgate to Tiburne to execution, and wilt thou not much more grieue to ſee thy ſelfe and others to goe from hence to hell to execution and endles torments?</p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider the examples of holy men, firſt
<pb facs="tcp:4334:13"/> of our Sauiour, he wept to ſee the graceleſneſſe of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, that ſhe would not when ſhee might be viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Lord hauing ſo kindly as he had often times viſited her, by ſending to her early and late, but alas ye weepe not that ye haue done this, reſiſted the trueth as <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> you being men of corrupt mindes &amp; reprobate concerning the truth. <hi>Lot</hi> hee was vexed from day to day, neuer had merry day nor night becauſe of the filthineſſe of the <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites.</hi> The people of God in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> time mourned for the iniquities of the people. <hi>Ieremiah</hi> wept night and day for the ſlaine of the daughter of his people, but alas what doe theſe preuaile? O let them bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes before thine eyes, &amp; in thy heart, yea, let them be as thy ſignet vpon thy right hand, to mooue thee to bee farre from making thy ſelfe merry with thine owne and others ſinnes. Shall Chriſt weepe for Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem becauſe ſhee will not heare? and wilt thou laugh to ſee <hi>England</hi> and the men thereof ſtop their eares againſt the voyce of the Charmer? ſhall <hi>Lot</hi> be vexed from day to day with the filthineſſe of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites, and wilt thou with the vncleanneſſe of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> from day to day at bed and at board make thy ſelfe merry?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Conſider the ouglineſſe of ſinne, what it coſt thy Sauiour, it is moſt ougly and filthy, and the ſmell of it moſt noiſome in the noſtrils of Gods Saints, and canſt thou reioyce at it, lift vp thy head and be merry thereat? alas if thou come through the cloſe ſtreetes of the City, which are for the moſt part moſt noiſom, thou wilt looke downeward, ſtop thy noſe, and ſhew
<pb facs="tcp:4334:13"/> thy diſlike of thoſe filthy ſmels by thy ſpeeches, and yet thou canſt come by, yea, walke by and talke with theſe filthy dunghils of the world, belching out more filthy ſmels then all the dunghils in the Citie, and yet thou canſt hold vp thy head, and laugh at the ſame, pitifull and lamentable to beholde, eſpecially this being found there, and in thoſe perſons, where and by whom ſinne ſhould be moſt puniſhed. As in your ſpirituall courts. You make but a tuſh of ſinne, yea of whoredome it ſelfe: you can and doe make your ſelues merrie both in your Courts and elſe-where, with the things there related. If this will not preuaile to root out this euill, let the conſideration of the work our ſinne had in our Sauiour moue vs. Oh wilt thou reioyce at that which made him heauie, and ſad? ſhall that make thee laugh, ſo that teares ſhall paſſe from thine eies with ioy, which made our Sauiour to ſhed both water &amp; blood? O beloued, let it neuer be ſaid, that thou art ſo grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and little reſpectiue of Chriſt thy Sauiour, whom thou laboureſt hereby to crucifie againe, and doeſt no leſſe then laugh him to ſcorne.</p>
            <q>Out of the word ſignifying iniustice, eſpecially meant in this place, we learne.</q>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> That loue ſeeketh not by iniuſtice to inrich her ſelfe. It taketh no delight to bee made rich by iniuſtice, which the examples of holy men in Scripture euery where witneſſe, as firſt of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who refuſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with fleſh and bloud, and therefore would depend vpon God, rather then to labour ro continue his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour,
<pb facs="tcp:4334:14"/> or better his eſtate by dealing iniuſtly with his Maiſter, importuned ſo to doe by his Miſtris. Like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which is that example of <hi>Iacob,</hi> who would no way iniurie his Maiſter to enrich himſelfe, and therefore hee clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth himſelfe, by ſaying, That whatſoeuer is found more with him then couenant, namely what ſheepe or goates were found more then thoſe that had little or great ſpots of black vpon them, with him, ſhould be theft vnto him.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.33.</note> A patterne worth the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing for ſeruants both bond and free in our daies: If all ſhold be theft (as it is in truth before God) that they haue taken and filched from their Maiſters more then their wages, all the priſons in London would not be able to hold all the theeues in London, for either flatly and plainly doe they play the theeues, or elſe more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiquely, and that they will ſtand in defence of to be no theft, to ſell their Maiſters wares, to allow him ſo much as he priſeth them at, and by which they knowe he may be an honeſt gainer, &amp; the reſt keepe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. On riches of iniquitie, and heerein doe you commit two ſinnes, theft with your Maiſter, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion with others, by haling them to a greater price then indeede you ſhould. And as he did not by theft labour to inrich himſelfe, neither did he by his laſie, negligent, and halfe ſeruing of his Maiſter; hee beſtowed all the time he ſhould vpon his Maiſters bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, he did not loue his bed better then his Maiſters buſineſſe, for his ſleepe departed from his eies, neither did he ſhrinke for the heate of the day, or the colde of the night, for ſaith hee, I was in the day conſumed with heate, and with froſt in the night, and my ſleepe
<pb facs="tcp:4334:14"/> departed from mine eies. <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.40. And as this holy man was farre from ſeeking to inrich himſelfe by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull and vniuſt courſes: So <hi>Paul</hi> proteſteth that he was farre from the ſame, which hee auoucheth as a teſtimonie of his loue (though not requited with loue againe) to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15.16.17. This do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine will appeare more dilucidly in the trueth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: If wee conſider that where loue hath beene wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, there men haue not cared by iniuſt courſes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelues, as <hi>Ahab</hi> to get <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard by murder, <hi>Abſolon</hi> to aſpire to the Kingdome by flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and <hi>Iudas</hi> to betray his Maiſter vpon enuie and haſtie anger.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> Loue teacheth vs to doe to, and by others, as wee would haue others to doe to, and by our ſelues.</q>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> To examine by our iuſt dealing and direct courſes, taken to enrich our ſelues by, what loue is amongſt vs, and at whoſe houſe, and in whoſe perſon true loue dwelleth: but alas no where, or but in few places is true loue, the loue of God to be found; but the loue of the Diuell, who alwaies hath, and euer will labour to enrich himſelfe, by accuſing of the Brethren, lying to <hi>Ahab,</hi> by his falſe Prophets, falſe cyting of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to our Sauiour Chriſt, Equiuocating, and ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall cauilling; according to which, doe the men of our daies labour to enrich themſelues, by accuſing of men better then themſelues, by lying and deceitfull ſpeeches, which they ſpread as a Net, to entrapp thoſe that deale and traffique with them by: But that I may
<pb facs="tcp:4334:15"/> come a little neerer, and faſten this Naile a little faſter, let me ranke you into your ſeuerall rankes, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, your ſeuerall trickes of iniuſtice, that we may ſee if true loue dwelleth in this Citie, or almoſt in any place of the world. Firſt, for Church-men, doth loue dwell amongſt you? let your iniuſtice ſpeake: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, You Noble-men, hath it any better entertainment amongſt you? your oppreſſion, crueltie, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible theeuery of ſome of you, ſhall witnes: You Lawyers, is it better accepted amongſt you? your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting of iuſtice and iudgement, and more then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable bribery will ſay noe: You Tradſemen, in what Company of you dwelleth loue? your falſe and deceitfull trickes will ſing, not in our Company wee are ſure: You Cheaters, your cunny-catching, and roguiſh trickes, will ſay, not with vs; and ſo it will proue, loue is no where entertained.</p>
            <p>That iniuſtice hath built her neſt in the Church, let the indirect courſes taken by Church-men, at their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, and afterwards to make themſelues great, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: In entrance, not grace and gifts from God, but droſſe and gifts from men preuaile, Patrons ſelling their liuings as commonly, as horſes are ſoulde in Smith-fielde, at the firſt motion, ſaying, <hi>quantum dabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> vnto which, the partie to be preſented, willing to giue eare, aunſwereth, We may not deale ſo plainely and directly, let vs carry matters more handſomely, leaſt the law (of man he meaneth, he neuer thinketh of God in thoſe matters) take holde of vs; and therefore behold your ſeueral iniuſt, and vnlawfull courſes, you haue to enter by: If you cannot come to parle with
<pb facs="tcp:4334:15"/> the Patron, then you will vndermine him by his wife, and you will not ſticke to giue her twenty or fortie pounds to buy her a Gown or a Nagge, ſo that ſhe wil ſtand your good Miſtris, and ſpeake for you: If that will not doe, then betake you your ſelues to your young Maſter; and that he may not be meale-mouth'd you will beſtow vpon him a couple of Dogges, or a Gelding of tenne pounds: If this will not ſerue, then you will lay waite in euery corner and place, and therefore will be ſure to beſtow angels liberally vpon his attendants, that they may helpe you forward, and lift you vp to come in by the Windowes: And if all this will not do, then you haue an <hi>Vltimum refugium,</hi> And that is, to enter into bonds with the Patron to pay him an hundred pounds, or ſome ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie without mentioning of and in conſideration of ſuch a Benefice, or liuing beſtowed (that were too plaine dealing) by vertue whereof, the Patron may driue the partie after inſtitution and induction, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with him, that hee may ſhare with him. Are not theſe things ſo (beloued)? and are not theſe the ſtaires that lead vp to the Window? what euils they haue brought vpon our Church (euen the placing of idle and inſufficient perſons, becauſe they can procure more friends, or haue greater purſes, and the like) I will ceaſe to ſpeake.</p>
            <p>And from this firſt, I will come to the ſecond kind of iniuſtice in Church-men, and that is after they are entred in: they are of two ſorts, either non-reſidents, or reſidents: non-reſidents are thoſe which haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny liuings, or but two: theſe men doe ſeeke to enrich
<pb facs="tcp:4334:16"/> themſelues by vſury, for of all, theſe are the moſt intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable vſurers, worſe then Aldermen, whoſe trade it is, to whom I ſhall ſpeak anone. For they will take but tenne or twenty vpon the hundred, but theſe non-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make an hundred of tenne: nay, they will haue one ſet ouer their one hundred or two hundred pound liuings happily to poſt from one to another, as a foote-boy to doe his Maiſters arrand, whereby they deale vniuſtly to reape the fleece, and not feeding the flocke, putting in hirelings and inſufficients into their roome, whilſt they lie at the ſpring and vvell head of promotion, as in this Citie, or ſome Cathedrall place, that when the ladder of promotion is emptie, they may ſtep vp, which brings to my minde that picture of a non-reſident, which was thus pictured with two liuings in both hands, with two at his feete, and with two in his pockets, and yet he gaped for another: haue we not ſuch Church-men in our daies? now to reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and thoſe are of three ſorts, which iniuſtly inrich themſelues, as firſt thoſe which are able to preach, but are laſie and idle, feeding their people when they can a while. Secondly, ſuch as take vpon them to preach and can but babble, vttering froth in ſteade of ſound doctrine, as the euill blood and humors in their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhew.</p>
            <p>The third are dumbe dogges, and ſuch as cannot preach (the burden and bane of our Church) theſe and euery of theſe by iniuſtice inrich themſelues receauing the fleece; but ſparingly, corruptly, and not at all, teaching their people: and thus you ſee Church-men are the ſeates of iniuſtice, by which they haue driuen
<pb facs="tcp:4334:16"/> loue out of the Church, then in <hi>Eccleſia nulla charitas.</hi> Now from the Church I will deſcend to the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Gentrie of our Land, to ſee if loue dwell in theſe Noble hearts: alas, alas, a man may as ſoone finde a knot in a bull-ruſh, as any true loue heere, for heere is nothing in many of them but robbing and ſpoiling of the poore, and thoſe that are too weake for them. Are not moſt of you Church-robbers, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the tenths from the Church, the Leuites porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? and doe not you daily imbeſſell the right of the Church from her, by pulling backe that which is due to the Miniſter? yea, ſome of you are ſuch greedie earthwormes, that you will ſhare and part ſtakes with the Miniſter you preſent, elſe he ſhall haue no benefice from you: alas what will you do at that generall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, when you ſhal ſtand before him, whom you haue robbed and ſpoiled improperly, hauing made the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of his ſeruants yours, you will be found not onely theeues (though now incorrigible) but murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of the ſoules of the people, by keeping that in your hands, ſhould maintaine the ſtewards of Gods houſe, that might giue them their portion in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: but leauing this, let vs come to take a view of your iuſt dealing in your temporall eſtates, alas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold nothing but oppreſſion, and grinding the face of the poore, alwaies looking and caſting how you may receiue much to ſpend vpon your luſts, or to hoord vp againſt the day of wrath, neuer thinking what they ſhal haue for their mony, to whom you let your lands, ſo that I may now ſay, that Land-lords are become the racks of their tenants, for a worſe racke they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:4334:17"/> prouide for them, then to diſtract them and pull them in pieces, as they doe, by cauſing them to carpe and care night and day, how to pay them that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort of them, houſe and houſhold being vnprouided for: and is heere all? No. Behold what iniuſt courſes they vſe to get that they haue, and to ioine houſe to houſe, might not right, for by their might doe they wreſt the law out of the hands of the poore and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and by that, which ſhould be their ſword to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them, doe they thruſt them out of houſe and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, that many of them dwell vpon lands and in hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they haue come to by robberie and crueltie. Let the manie hundreds and thouſands, manie of them haue comming yearely in, ariſing from Church-liuings and lands gotten by might not right, the horſes they ride on, the meate they feede vpon, the ſilkes and ſat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin ſutes they iet vp and downe in, bought with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes of ſuch land, witneſſe the ſame. Doe they not ſtretch themſelues vpon beds, drinke their wine in bowles, haue they not their great chambers &amp; dining Parlours hung with hangings, bought with money which is none of their owne, but iniuſtly kept and held from the owner after the day: doe they not daily build houſes with the wages of vnrighteouſneſſe, doe they not keepe back their ſeruants wages, and vſe the helpe of their neighbours, without giuing them for their trauaile? Doe they not rob both Countrie and the poore, to maintaine their pompe. Let the manifolde legacies they keepe in their hands bequeathed to the poore, and to charitable vſes, as making of bridges and mending the high waies, witneſſe the ſame. So
<pb facs="tcp:4334:17"/> that here this Quaere of Loue hath as bad ſucceſſe as in the Church; Noblemen and Gentlemen, are as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt as any.</p>
            <p>Let vs put this Quaere to Lawyers, is there any loue amongſt moſt of you? Alas, methinkes moſt of you anſwere me <hi>Nodum in ſcirpo quaeris,</hi> if you ſeeke for Loue here: Which, that common Prayer of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of our age doth verifie, for whereas they had wont to pray to be deliuered from the deuill and Hell, now they pray to be deliuered from Law and Lawyers, but how iuſtly they doe this, let the ſeuerall trickes you haue to inrich your ſelues by, teſtifie; Doe not you ſerue your owne turnes vpon your Clients, bearing them in hand their cauſe is good, when you know it to be ſtarke-naught, like the falſe Prophets to <hi>Ahab?</hi> Are not you ſuch, many of you, that beſides your Fee you will take a Bribe to procure a day of hearing? Doe not you make law a noſe of waxe, conſtruing it as you pleaſe, making that Law now which ſhortly ſhall bee none? Doe not you keepe matters, cauſes and Suites longer depending then needes, and for no other ende but that you may pull Clients bare, and feather your owne neſts with their feathers? Doe you heare and Pleade and Iudge matters and caſes betwixt man and man, without reſpecting perſons? Doth the cauſe of Widdowes and the Fatherleſſe come before you, as well as the cauſe of the rich and mightie? The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of many to the contrarie ſay, there is no ſuch thing. And that you may fulfill the meaſure of your Iniuſtice, you will haue about with God, to ſteale his time from him: For, doe not you (Right Reuerend
<pb facs="tcp:4334:18"/> Iudges) ride your Circuits vpon the Lords day vſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and referre matters to bee heard priuately in your Chambers? I beſeech you let theſe things bee amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And you that are of the Temples and Innes, in and about this Citie, doe you not ſteale the Lords time? Are not your Staires troad, and your Chambers frequented, as much vpon the Sabboth as vpon other dayes? This cannot be denied, which plainely conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that Iniuſtice is riſe amongſt you, and therefore no true loue. Which of you can ſay with <hi>Iob, The bleſsing of him that was ready to periſh came vpon mee?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 29.13.</note> Nay, may you not more truely ſay, the curſings of them that were ready to periſh, come and are vpon vs; for our Iniuſtice? Let the bitter curſes of more then a fewe,<note place="margin">Praeoc.</note> witneſſe what I ſay. As I approoue not their curſing, ſo know you that offences will come, but woe be to them by whom offences doe come.</p>
            <p>Which of you can ſay, that you haue put on Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 14.</note> and that couereth you, and that your Iudgement is a Crowne and Robe vnto you? Nay, rather can you not more truely ſay, you haue vſed Iniuſtice and that couereth you? You haue peruerted Iuſtice and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that is it that hath brought ſo many Crownes, Angels and Robes vnto you? Can you ſay that when you knew not the cauſe, you ſought it out diligently? Few or none of you can ſo ſay. If the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and cauſe be ambiguous and troubleſome, doe not you refuſe to meddle in it? Or if you be importuned thereunto? Doe you not ſo ſhuffle and daube it ouer, that when it commeth to bee looked into againe, it proueth worſe then at the firſt, like an olde Wound
<pb facs="tcp:4334:18"/> that was not healed to the bottome? Theſe things are more then plaine amongſt many of you, as wofull and daily experience ſheweth, whereby it appeareth that there is no Loue amongſt you to bee found, and that all this while in ſeeking Loue amongſt you, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum in ſcirpo quaeſiui.</hi> From you, let mee come to Tradeſmen, what ſay you, is there any more Loue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you? I doubt it ſore, your indirect courſes to inrich your ſelues by, ſay you haue no Loue amongſt you.</p>
            <p>Firſt to begin with you Aldermen, doe not you as you come into place of Magiſtracie ſell the Offices of Sergeants, Yeomen, and the like vnder you? Some for twentie Pound, ſome for fortie Pound, ſome for an hundred Pound? If this be ſo (as the complaint is) you hereby teſtifie that Loue is far from amongſt you. Doe not you oppreſſe others by the diuers Taskes, Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenes, and Impoſitions, and your vnequall Ceffing of men therein, ſo that they which worſt may do beare the burden? I accuſe not any of you, let euery ſoule ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine himſelfe, the generall voice is, you doe this; if you doe it, can you ſay there is any Loue amongſt you to lay heauie burdens vpon others, that you may goe light laden? Doe not you put your money to Vſurie? Yes, let that epethite (though commonly ſpoken, yet peculiar appropriated to you) Vſurie the Aldermans Trade, witneſſe this: And is this nothing (Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and Right Worſhipfull) that I may ſay no more then <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> did of Ieruſalem:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.2.</note> Let mee ſay ſo much! O bloody London, becauſe with many other ſinnes, thy Inhabitants,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 12.</note> eſpecially moſt of thy Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb facs="tcp:4334:19"/> haue taken Vſurie, and the increaſe and defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their neighbours by Extortion: by all which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that amongſt the chiefe of you, that haue to doe in Trading in this Citie, there is no Loue. And if we deſcend to the inferiour ſort, we ſhall find as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: For, doe not thoſe which are rich amongſt you like Pickrels, labour to eate vp all the reſt? And that either by ouer-ſelling the poorer and meaner ones, or elſe by ingroſſing all into their hands, that the meaner ſhall be driuen to come and buy at their hands: And to pay ſuch a price for euery commoditie, that he can not liue by ſelling the ſame againe, and therefore muſt be conſtrained either to be come ſlaue to the greater, or elſe to doe worſe? Doe not you vſually falſifie your weights by deceite, haue you not one weight and meaſure to ſell by, and another to buy by? Haue you not a falſe Ballance, and a bagge of falſe Weights which the Lord hateth? Doe you not prey vpon the ignorance and neceſſities of men in buying, ſelling, and lending? Doe you not prey vpon the neceſſitie of the time, as againſt this time (which you cal the good-time and holy dayes, though in regard of the abuſe and prophaneſſe of them; they may now iuſtly be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len the bad time and worſt of dayes) doe you not ſet to ſale your worſt Wares and Commodities, and ſet good gloſſes vpon the ſame, ſaying, lying, and ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, it is the beſt, when there is no ſuch matter: And you only doe this, that you may prey vpon the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of the time, and the wants of men which muſt needes be ſupplied, all which, with your cozening, and calling of good, bad, in buying; and bad, good in ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb facs="tcp:4334:19"/> teſtifie that amongſt you trades-men there is no loue to be found, ſeeing iniuſt and indirect meanes are in euery ſort of you vſed to inrich your ſelues by: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs in the laſt place come to cheaters, and ſee whether direct dealing dwell there, let vs take a view of their courſes, they take for their victuals, cloathes, horſes, and ſpending money, and we ſhall be conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to conclude, that loues houſe is nullibi in theſe daies. For the prouiding of their victuals, beholde how with impudent trickes they can draw young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to tauernes, for dinners or ſuppers, and when all is done, by one ſlie ſubtill tricke or other finely put it from themſelues, and vpon the Gallants to pay for all, it will not otherwaies ſtand with their honours, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, or reputations. Now you ſee the impudent tricks they haue to victuall the campe, let vs ſee if they haue anie better to cloath it withall: to the Taylor or Mercer they goe, and there take vp their ſuites, neuer ſtand vpon termes and priſes, but let them haue their owne asking, (but you muſt vnderſtand when they can get it) they will promiſe payment (for fewe ſuch pay downe) and giue faire words, and as manie bonds as they will haue, but to pay what they owe, is the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt from their thoughts. Thus they deale for their apparrell, for their horſes and ſpending monie, they haue waies more then manie, their father the diuell whom they ſerue hath taught them well. So that they by their long being with, and much obſeruation of the gallants and young Gentlemen of our daies, ſee how they are diſpoſed, and accordinglie fit their humours, if to hawkes, then that way; if to hounds then, that: if
<pb facs="tcp:4334:20"/> to horſes, then that; if to harlots, then that; if to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling, then that way: ſo that at length by their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moring of them, they coſen them with a crackt groat, and ſerue their turnes vpon them, and by this meanes haue as good horſes, and as large a purſe as the beſt of them all. Thus doe you ſee (beloued) that loue is no where, becauſe iniuſtice is euery where: but what is the cauſe that iniuſtice thus ouer-ſpreadeth our land, and all degrees in the ſame: The Apoſtle telleth you, the want of loue, vnto which I may adde the ſinne of our firſt parents aſpiring mindes, that we cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelues to be as God would haue vs, wee will be houſed, meated, apparrelled, and attended accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the faſhion, and the beſt, not according to our eſtate &amp; place. Secondly, want of truſting God, truſting him no further then we ſee him, the ſinne of the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering Iſraelites: and thirdly, preſuming that by our owne power wee can helpe our ſelues. Let vs then (beloued) to remoue this generall iniuſtice, labour to loue one another more and more, and that not in word but in deede, let vs be content with the Lords faſhion and allowance; if hee will haue thee to weare cloath, doe not thou weare veluet, if hee would haue thee to put but one yard into thy garment, put not in two: If hee would haue thee to haue but one length in thy band or ruffe, put not in more. Truſt God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou ſee him not, and knowe that the helpe of man is naught worth, no man is able by his owne care to adde one cubite vnto his ſtature. So ſhall iniuſtice fade and decay, but loue and honeſt dealing flouriſh more and more: that I may perſwade you heereto, I
<pb facs="tcp:4334:20"/> will endeuour my ſelfe to lay downe ſeuerall motiues and practiſes, as helpes and furtherances herein: ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vanity and vnprofitableneſſe of that we ſo by iniuſtice ſearch after; the firſt conſideration, is this.</p>
            <p>That which wee ſo labour and toile our ſelues to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> obtaine per fas or nefas, is vncertaine and a matter of nothing, for what is it but riches, and by conſequence honour, worſhip, and reputation, whereof the wiſe man plainely affirmeth, that it is nothing.<note place="margin">Prou. 23.5</note> Why wilt thou caſt thy eies vpon it, which is nothing? for riches taketh her to her wings, as an Eagle and flieth into the heauen, of which opinion is the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in that his Epiſtle to <hi>Timothie.</hi> 1.6.7. Charge them which are rich in this world, that they be not high minded, and that they truſt not in vncertaine riches. Which the example of that great rich man mentioned <hi>Luke</hi> 12.21.22. plainly confirmeth: Ouer night he had ſo much that he lacked roome to lay what he had in, but in the morning all was nothing: ſo is euery one that is rich in this world, and not rich in God: lay this to thy ſoule, and often conſider it to ſtay thee from iniuſt courſes to inrich thy ſelfe by, for when thou haſt that thou ſeekeſt for, thou haſt, that thou haſt no certaintie of, and in truth a matter of nothing, and is it not mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for nothing thus to toile thy ſelfe and iniure others?</p>
            <p>To ſuch a man as thou deſireſt to be, is pronounced a woe, <hi>Luke.</hi> 6.24. <hi>vae vobis diuitibus,</hi> which neuer is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> done againſt the poore. What heart canſt thou haue to ſeeke for ſuch an eſtate, and that iniuſtly too, which hath a woe belonging to it? Conſider this well, and it
<pb facs="tcp:4334:21"/> will make thee feare to be rich, and to walke thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in pouerty.</p>
            <p>It is an eſtate that maketh men ſlacke to Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, hardly to be drawne to God, and when they are drawne to him, a great meanes to pull them backe, as both experience and Scriptures witneſſe. Who ſeeth it not, but that they which are rich, are the tardieſt commers to the Church, and holy exerciſes of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? Vpon the Sabboth they cannot attend at the poſts of the dore of the Church, but muſt be attended vpon, the whole Church and congregation muſt ſtay vpon them, if they come to the Sermon it is well, they haue no part nor portion in prayer, what is the cauſe of this, they are ſo curiouſly to bee dreſſed, that the whole morning is too little for that, or elſe they haue accompts to take, or one thing or other to confer of, that they can come no ſooner. And as they are tardy commers, ſo, who ſo infrequent there as theſe perſons? they haue farmes, or yokes of Oxen, or the like, that they cannot come, if once of the day, they thinke that ſufficient, if twiſe, they thinke that more then needeth, and that then God is ſo beholding to them, that hee muſt of deſert, and in liew of that ſeruice vouchſafed that day, allow them the reſt of the Sabboth before and after, either for their worldly commodities or cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed delights. Beſides all this, who ſo hardly drawne to Chriſt as they? they are like to Pickrels not eaſily nor often taken, a man may take twentie Pinkes and leſſer fiſhes before one Pickrell, for hee preieth ſo ſore at his pleaſure vpon the leſſer fiſhes, that hee ſeldome or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath any ſtomacke to bite at the bait, and ſo fareth
<pb facs="tcp:4334:21"/> it with the rich men of the world, their ſtomacks are ſo cloyed with the cruſts and hard fare of the things of this life, that when the doctrine of ſaluation is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, they haue no appetite thereto; the young man found it to be true, nothing hindred his comming to Chriſt but the loſſe of his riches: vntill our Sauiour tolde him, that muſt be the thing he muſt part withall, who forwarder then hee? This hardneſſe that experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence letteth vs ſee, our Sauiour taught vs, ſaying, <hi>It is as hard for a rich man to come to the Kingdome of heauen, as for a cable to goe through the eye of a needle;</hi> and not only this, but they are meanes to draw men from God, as <hi>Lots</hi> wiues example teſtifieth, and daily experience witneſſeth. O let theſe conſiderations enter into thy heart, and ceaſe thou by iniuſtice to ſeeke that which is ſuch an enemie to thee in comming to holy exerciſes, and hinderers of thee from comming to Chriſt, &amp; pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of thee from him, when thou haſt laide hold on him.</p>
            <p>They are dangerous in getting and not ſafe in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, who ſeeth it not, that it is a hard thing for a man <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> to be rich and keepe a good conſcience, and wallie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly with God. And therefore may I well compare the climbing vp to preferment, and the getting of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, to a tree who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e boughes and leaues be hung and clogged with hony, vnto which when a hungry man commeth, hee falleth of licking one leafe and bough after another, vntill he is caried ſo high from one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, through the greedineſſe of his hunger, that he ſlippeth &amp; ſlideth, and cannot ſtay himſelfe but downe he commeth and breaketh legge or arme, if hee ſcape
<pb facs="tcp:4334:22"/> with life. So dangerous (beloued) is it to climbe vp the tree of riches, for moſt commonly men lay holde ſo vpon one hundred after another, and one thouſand after another, that they endanger themſelues ſore, if they eſcape with ſaluation of ſoule and body. And truly as they are thus dangerous in comming by, ſo they are not leſſe dangerous in vſing &amp; keeping them, for how can a man lie in a bed of thornes, and not be prickt? or how can a man feede vpon little fiſhes full of bones and not be in danger of choaking, without good take heede? Let this moue vs to eaſe from clim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing by iniuſtice to riches ſo dangerous in getting, and no leſſe in keeping.</p>
            <p>Conſider what thou ſhalt leaue to thy children, if <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> thou leaue them goods thus gotten, not that thou weeneſt, thou were better to leaue them beggers then thus. For thou leaueſt them in an vnquiet poſſeſſion, hauing God their enemie, and howſoeuer thy children proue, they cannot be good to them. If godly, then they will be continuall griefes to them, to ſee thoſe in their poſſeſſion, for which their father is gone to the diuell: If worldlings like thy ſelfe, thou haſt made them able to build on, as thou haſt begun, the tower of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell: if prodigall, then thou haſt taken the way to make him more prodigall, then which to haue ſeene in thy life time, thou hadſt rather haue beene childleſſe, in that he had not beene borne, or in hauing him taken from thee before thee by death: O then (beloued) why wilt thou labour thus to much thy ſelfe, and to hoord vp in this manner that, which neither is good for thee nor thy children after thee.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4334:22"/>
            <p>Conſider the little auaile and profit that is in theſe things: What euils did they free thee from? not from <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> ſickneſſe I am ſure, for the rich is ſicke as well as the poore; will they comfort thee vpon thy death-bed, when thy conſcience is awaked in horror and griefe? No. And therefore thou canſt not endure the ſight of them, they being as ſo many witneſſes, foretelling to thee thy damnation: whereupon it is, that thou ſaieſt thou art dead to the world, &amp; haſt put all earthly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters out of thy ſight, and why doeſt thou ſo? not for any minde thou haſt to leaue them, but to ſtop the mouth of thy conſcience, which could not reſt accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and tormenting thee whilſt thou hadſt them in thy hand. But albeit they cannot free thee heere from paine, nor comfort thee vpon thy death-bed, it may be they can free thee from hell; no ſuch matter, all that a man hath is too little to free a mans ſoule from thence, <hi>Diues</hi> muſt to hell from all his riches, becauſe he would not part with them to the poore, much more the rich men of our daies, that not onely will not giue to the poore, but by all meanes they can take from them. Oh let this enter into thy heart, and if none of the former conſiderations will preuaile with thee, let this, to ſtay thee from further ſeeking, there is no more auaile in riches then in pouerty. Now let vs come to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, which are three: the firſt is prayer, &amp; that which <hi>Dauid</hi> hath taught: <hi>Encline my heart vnto thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and not to couetouſneſſe;</hi> this prayer, howſoeuer it is entertained, I am ſure it is not practiſed: which muſt be, if euer you will come to the practiſe of iuſtice. You would haue liked me better if I had put couetouſneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:4334:23"/> in the place of thy teſtimonies, and thy teſtimonies in the place of couetouſneſſe. Vſe this prayer, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſtriue with the Lord, and thou ſhalt ſee the effect ſure, for he is faithfull that hath promiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Conſider in euery thing thou doeſt, in thy buying, ſelling, purchaſing, and taking poſſeſſion, lending and receauing, that thou muſt giue account of what thou doeſt, yea, alwaies thinke thou heareſt the Lord ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in thy eares this ſentence, <hi>Redde rationem villicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis tuae,</hi> which will be a meanes, and that an excellent one, to cauſe thee to looke to thy waies, leaſt by iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice thou reape to thy ſelfe damnation.</p>
            <p>Take more then ordinarie paines, as thou caſteſt thy <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> booke daily and yearely to ſee, what and how much thou haſt taken, ſo goe once ouer it, and that with due deliberation and mature perpending of things, how rightly thou haſt inned that thou haſt, neuer forget this. Vſe theſe directions, and often meditate vpon theſe things, and I doubt not but through Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, they will bee excellent and forcible meanes to bring thee to loue &amp; embrace iuſtice more then thou doeſt. Which plainly ſheweth want of loue in thee, for true loue as thou haſt heard, ſeeketh not by iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to enrich her ſelfe. And thus haue I finiſhed the firſt part of my text, which is, <hi>Quid charitas abstinet:</hi> now to the latter, <hi>Quid efficit,</hi> in the laſt words of the verſe, which affordeth this point.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> That true loue reioyceth to ſee men deale iuſtly one towards another, &amp; religiouſly towards God. Which Doctrine hauing two parts, wee will accordingly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſame, and briefly diſpatch the firſt, which is,
<pb facs="tcp:4334:23"/> It is the propertie of true Loue to reioyce in Iuſtice and honeſt dealing betwixt man and man: Which trueth, the Lamentation of <hi>Ieremiah</hi> in his ninth doth plainely ſhew, weeping for the deceite and falſe dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his age: brother deceitfully dealing with bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As that alſo of <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.4.13. where hee ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his diſlike to ſee the people ſo oppreſſed, as that they were conſtrained to crie out, and to lay their Lands, Houſes, and Vineyards to gage for the Kings tribute, and to ſell them becauſe of the famine, this grieued theſe Holy men not a litle, the contrarie wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of would haue ioyed them much.</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> Becauſe Loue maketh vs to reioyce, as well in the well-doing and wel-hauing of others, as of our ſelues.</q>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> To teach vs to examine our ſelues, whether our Loue cauſe vs to doe this, to reioyce in doing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing Iuſtice one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, this concerneth euery man in his own practiſe, and thoſe that are vnder him; as your Children and Seruants. You that haue Shops and are Lords, doe you delight in it? And willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly permit thoſe that are vnder you to doe the ſame? It is an Argument Loue dwelleth at thy houſe. You that haue Offices, doe you the like? I feare it much, but eſpecially doe you (Right Honourable) ſhew your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing herein, by your inquiring and ſearching out (by your many eares and eyes) the deceitfull courſes vſed by Weights and Meaſures, and ſetting to ſale corrupted Wares in your Citie, to the hurt of the Subiects? Looke to it, if you doe it, you ſhewe you haue true Loue to God your ſelfe, in keeping your Officers, and your Citie to preſerue the mutuall good
<pb facs="tcp:4334:24"/> of the ſame, but I feare this ſore (Right Honourable) the many exclamations and complaints here, argue the contrarie, O looke to this, if you will haue any comfort in thinking your ſelf to be free from periurie, which will not onely ſtaine thee, but brand thy poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie after thee, that both thou and they, ſhall bee tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the worſe againe whilſt you liue. And from this we will proceede to the ſecond part of this Doctrine, which I onely will inſiſt vpon, being thus much.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[That Loue reioyceth.]</hi> To ſee men walke in the trueth, that is to be Religious towards God; Which the example of <hi>Dauid</hi> in the 122. <hi>Pſal. ver.</hi> 1. plainely proueth, who faith hee reioyced when they ſaid, <hi>Come let vs goe to the houſe of the Lord.</hi> Together with that 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 15.14.15. Where it is ſaid, the people reioyced to ſee all ſo ready to take the Oath for the ſeruice of the true God: as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and the people did, to ſee the Prieſts ſo ready to purge the Temple, <hi>Ibid.</hi> 29.36. and the reioycing in fetching vp the Arke ſheweth the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label>
               <hi>Becauſe ſuch are ſeruants to the moſt mightie Lord, and it doth them good to ſee their Maſter well attended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label>
               <hi>True Loue maketh vs to wiſh, euery one to be as we are, and therefore a Chriſtian neuer deſireth to goe alone, but would haue companie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> To examine our ſelues what Loue there is in vs, by our reioycing to ſee men walke in the trueth, and to be truely Religious towards God, which will proue vs all too farre from that wee ſhould bee, as both our proceedings againſt ſuch perſons, and our ſpeeches of them before their faces, and behind their backes plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:4334:24"/> ſhew, which all tend to the diſgracing of them and their Holy profeſſion. If a man will but pray with his family, Euening and Morning, Catechiſe them, and cal them to an account what they haue heard, refraine himſelfe from Tauernes, Playes, and other companie of good fellowes, falſely ſo called, hee is made like an Owle in the wilderneſſe amongſt you, hee is hated of his neighbours, euill ſpoken of vndeſeruedly, and his cauſes and Suites ſhall fare the worſe for them. Is this to reioyce to ſee men forward in Religion? Nay, is it not to grieue becauſe they bee ſo, which is to enuie at Gods good eſtate to be ſo well attended: This ſinne, the ſinne peculiar to England aboue all Nations, is euery where to be found. Is there any people that will hate them that are forward in their owne Religion? And yet wee doe, that a man will ſerue God but in good earneſt, and make care of keeping his word and vowe with GOD, in forſaking the deuill and all his workes, is hee not preſently named a Preſcitian and groſſe hypocrite, and yet doth nothing but that which thou muſt doe, except thou wilt prooue a promiſe breaker and periured perſon before God. The Papiſts and Turkes in renowming thoſe that haue beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeſt in their Religion, ſhall riſe vp at the day of Iudgement to condemne the Engliſh people, who are moſt hatefull to them that ſerue God moſt intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which ſheweth litle reioycing in the truth amongſt vs, and ſo conſequently, little or no true Loue at all. Now that I may leaue you without doubt in this point, I will lay downe ſome ſeuerall markes whereby you may know, whether you reioyce in Religion, and
<pb facs="tcp:4334:25"/> in the happie ſucceſſe thereof, yea or no. The firſt whereof: A reioycing in the trueth, becauſe it is the trueth, and for no other reſpects, ſaying and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming as <hi>Iob, Though thou kill me, I will not forſake thee:</hi> And with our Sauiours Diſciples, Whither ſhall wee goe Lord, thou haſt the word of eternall life, which is the vndoubted marke of a true Louer of Religion. Hereby let you Church-men examine your ſelues? Doe you profeſſe Religion, and hold your places in pretence of maintaining the ſame, becauſe it is trueth, or rather becauſe of the ſweeteneſſe of the liuing you enioy thereby? You Profeſſors, doe you profeſſe out of meere loue to the trueth, or for ſiniſter reſpects? You Children, and ſuch as are vnder Gouernement, doe you it not rather becauſe you may thereby pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe more libertie to your ſelues. You Tradeſmen Profeſſors, doe not you profeſſe and onely ſeeme to reioyce in the trueth, becauſe you may gaine cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers thereby, and make it a couer for your couzning? You poorer ſort, doe not you likewiſe profeſſe for your bellies ſakes. I feare this much beloued, looke to it, if thou reioyceſt in the trueth, thou doeſt it ſimply becauſe it is the trueth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond marke of reioycing in the trueth is, if you labour to increaſe it and ſet it forward in thy own perſon, in thy family and the Countrey I ownes and Cities where thou dwelleſt. For the firſt, Paul would ſtriue himſelfe to know Chriſt, and preſſed forward towards the marke. <hi>Dauid</hi> would vow that he would keepe Gods righteous Iudgements: So that we muſt ſee what endeuouring there is to forward Religion in
<pb facs="tcp:4334:25"/> our ſelues, what care wee haue to growe and waxe in grace.</p>
            <p>What care haſt thou to forward Religion in thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> looke to this Miniſters and Noble-men whom it moſt concerneth, and by whom it is leaſt practiſed: for you Miniſters and Church-men, doe you anſwere the Apoſtles marke of a Miniſter,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4.</note> that he muſt be one that can rule his owne houſe honeſtly, hauing children vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der obedience with all honeſtie, and are you ſuch? are your houſes ruled honeſtly, and haue you children o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, and wiſe, ſober, honeſt, and not euill ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, but faithfull in all things.</p>
            <p>Now you Noble-men and Gentlemen, are your houſes any better gouerned? and doe you plant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion any more in your families then Church-men do in theirs? <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> reſolution is in few Noble-men and Gouernours of the people ſeene; <hi>I and my houſhold will ſerue the Lord.</hi> Doe you catechiſe and inſtruct your family, and pray with them in your owne perſons? Doe you giue thanks at the table for your ſelf, &amp; thoſe that dine with thee? Oh no, it is too baſe. Now (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) I know you are of two ſorts, ſome that thinke you are freed from this in your owne perſon, thoſe be ſuch of you that haue Chaplaines, who are in your ſteade, and ſo you will ſerue God by your Attourney, which doth diſmember the congregation, as it is now vſed, that when the greateſt part of the congregation is at publique place peaceable, and hearing or calling vpon God, the greateſt perſon with his traine is in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate ſeruing God, which is an vnſeemable doing of a good action, doing good in priuate when wee ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:4334:26"/> be publique. And theſe priuate exerciſes in families when we ſhould be in publique, cannot be warranted in the quiet and peaceable time of the Church, as now it is with vs. In the time of perſecution I know the Chriſtians met together in priuate families: ſecondly, it doth confound two diſtinct duties and callings in one perſon, namely in the Miniſter, when hee taketh vpon him to be a publique perſon, and a priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon too, vnto which he is not neceſſarily called, as hee is in his own family to be Maſter of a family, and ſo to diſcharge the duty of a Maſter in his houſe, and of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> publiquely.</p>
            <p>It freeth the Maiſter of the family from that dutie God hath required of him, in his owne perſon to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to his family, as to teach them in the Law of God, when he is at home and going abroad. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.7. which <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> &amp; all the holy men of God practiſed, and no Maiſter of a family is to be exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And laſtly, it maketh a Miniſter to looſe the liberty God hath graunted him, as to be ſubiect in his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, to the cenſure and iudgement of priuate men, whereas God wil haue the ſpirit of the Miniſter, to be ſubiect onely to the ſpirit of the Prophets, and our Church holdeth, that a man is to giue account of his Doctrine to the Ordinarie, and the cenſure thereof to abide. I ſay (theſe reaſons being well conſidered) it is queſtionable whether the ſtanding of a Chaplaine, as the Noble-men of England now would haue it, be warrantable. But ſuppoſe it were. What if thy Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine be inſufficient, as many be? being entertained ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:4334:26"/> to make thy ſelfe merrie withall, then to inſtruct thee or thy people, what wilt thou then doe? ſhal thy family not be inſtructed? doeſt thou thinke this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence will ſerue thy turne? but graunt thy Chaplaine be ſufficient, what if hee be laſie, idle, and careleſſe, as moſt be, being readier to play a game at the dice and cardes with thee, thy ſeruants and children, then to teach and catechiſe you, ſhall this beare thee out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God? no: if thy people periſh for want of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction priuately, you ſhall anſwer for the blood of their ſoules, as thou ſhouldeſt for the bloud of their bodies, if they periſhed by thy detaining of that from them, as meate, drinke, and wages, which thou art bound to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them. Were this a plea ſufficient to ſay, thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thy duty to thy childe, for thou committedſt him or her to a nurſe, whom thou kneweſt to be dry, and euery way inſufficient? No beloued, no more will it beare thee out to ſay thou haſt a Chaplaine, except thou ſee them inſtructed by thy owne perſon.</p>
            <p>Now then you Noble-men and Gentlemen, doe you forward Religion, by teaching your family, and praying with them? No, theſe doe not fit with your Greatneſſe, in trueth theſe heauenly things doe not fit with your baſeneſſe, and therefore thou wilt not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the ſame. God ſhall neuer be called vpon by thy family together, rather then thou wilt bee their mouth. God ſhall neuer be praiſed at the table, rather then thou wilt doe it, and therefore moſt commonly it is, that at ſuch mens tables, if the Chaplaine bee away and the children, grace and all is away, which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth all their ſeruice is but cuſtomarie, not of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:
<pb facs="tcp:4334:27"/> well, if this bee thy cuſtome, thou reioyceſt not in the truth, for thou doeſt not forward it in thy family by Doctrine &amp; example, which euery one doth that reioyceth in it. Doeſt thou ſee, ſay, and performe with <hi>Dauid, That no wicked perſon ſhall abide and dwell in thy houſe?</hi> No. For, alas where is the route and crew of ſuch, if not in your houſes? whither doe vncleane perſons, wantons, and bloud-ſhedders betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for ſhelter but to you? thinking if they once get your houſes ouer their heads, and your cloke or coate vpon their backes, then they are ſafe enough, as the Woodcock when he hath hid his head, and <hi>Adoniah</hi> when he fled to the hornes of the Altar. What ſhall I compare your houſes vnto? but to the fatteſt and fertileſt ground vntilled and vnhusbanded? which moſt commonly bringeth forth moſt weedes, and in which the moſt dangerous vermines doe abide. Looke vnto this, and either reforme it, or elſe confeſſe that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce not in the trueth, and ſo conſequently haue no true loue. This concerneth both ſorts of you, both that vnder pretence of Chaplaines will be careleſſe, and you alſo that without pretence thereof walke thus careleſly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> If thou deſire and endeuour the promoting and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of it where thou abideſt, in Country, Citie, or Towne, &amp; how do you further it here? truely there is little hope that you ſhould ſettle it there, ſeeing thou art farre from it in thy owne family. For as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of a Miniſter, how ſhal he care for the Church of God, if hee cannot rule his owne family? ſo how can it bee that you care to ſettle Religion in the places where
<pb facs="tcp:4334:27"/> you abide, if you be careleſſe of it in your owne fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies? what care you haue to further it in the places of your abode will the better appeare, if wee examine how yee vſe the meanes to further it there, which are of two ſorts: 1, either with men, 2, or God. With men, and thoſe are either, 1. the Church liuings thou haſt to beſtowe: 2. thy words and countenance: 3. thy purſe: 4. thy iourneying: 5. thy magiſtracie and authoritie.</p>
            <p>If thou vſe all theſe to furthering Religion in the place where thou dwelleſt, thou reioyceſt in the truth, if not, thou doeſt not, and ſo by conſequence no loue in thee. That we may the better perceiue this, let vs conſider theſe things in order. 1. Art thou carefull to beſtow theſe benefices and Church-liuings vpon able and ſufficient teachers? doe you commit holy things, as the ſoules of the people, the word of God and the Sacraments, to holy men, who haue vrim &amp; thummim, purity of life and ſoundneſſe of Doctrine: nay, rather are you not <hi>Ieroboams,</hi> that prefer to the place of the Miniſterie, the baggage and refuſe of men? the more by farre of ſuch now in the Church, then of ſufficient Preachers, doth teſtifie it to your ſhame: O let vs pray that theſe things were amended. Here had I thought to haue ſpoken to the reuerend Father of this Church, but let mee ſpeake to his eares and eies, that I would haue done to him, namely, that foraſmuch as Patrones bee careleſſe whom they preſent, but moſt commonly him that will giue moſt, or hath greateſt friends, caring not a iote to falſifie the truſt committed to them, O that it would pleaſe our Church gouernours to be carefull of
<pb facs="tcp:4334:28"/> theſe things, and to admit, inſtitute, and induct, none but men ſufficient, and therefore not to be ouer intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by great Perſons, nor importuned by flatterers about you, who for their Bribes, not for any goodwill to the Church, importune you. Thus by your care of beſtowing your Liuings, you may ſee whether you haue any ioy in Religion: yea, or no. But alas, by this it appeareth, that the Patrons of our dayes haue little Loue that way. For who ſeeketh for an able Miniſter, but one that is able to giue well for it, before hee haue it. Now let vs come to ſee what reioycing you haue in the truth, by vſing your word and countenance to profit the ſame?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Whom doe you ſpeake for, and vouchſafe a good word to? Is it for the diſtreſſed Iewes? Doſt thou ſpeake to <hi>Ahaſhueroſh</hi> in their behalfe? Doeth the benefit of thy words extend to the Saints that are vpon the earth? Doeſt thou further their cauſes, and defend them? Little of this beloued amongſt you, I would I might not ſay the quite contrarie, that your tongues are ſharpe arrowes and ſpeares againſt them, and that you are ſpeakers for and fauourers of Romane Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes, many of you, more then of Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thus by your words and countenance, you little ſhew your reioycing in the trueth, Let vs ſee what you doe with your Purſe? Doſt thou lay out thy money to haue the Darkenes remooued, and the Light (I meane the Goſpel of Chriſt) brought to thee? Doſt thou buy the trueth? Nay, rather do not you ſell it? As the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling of Church liuings, and Offices in theſe dayes rather ſhew? Doe you lay out your money to
<pb facs="tcp:4334:28"/> continue the ſincere and ſound Miniſterie of the word amongſt you? Nay, rather is it not to thruſt them out? For many ſpend that way, but few the other, is it to defend innocent and righteous perſons and cauſes? Nay, rather is it not to fee a Procter to ſpeake againſt them, whom thou vniuſtly ſlandereſt? Is it to buy good Bookes? No, rather to buy Play bookes, Ballads and wanton Sonnets, if not Popiſh bookes. Is it ſpent to relieue the Saints vpon the earth? No, but vpon the ſcumme of the world, Stage players, the bellowes of luſt, Fidlers, and Roguiſh Muſitians, by all which you ſhew plainely, you reioyce not in the trueth, for by laying out of your money, you ſhew the ſame. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
            </p>
            <p>And as in this, ſo I doubt you ſhew your ſelues little better in the next, which is your iournying: For, do you iourney with <hi>Ezra</hi> to ſeeke the Law of the Lord, and to teach it in Iſrael? Is it to good exerciſes? No, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is to thy whoriſh ſports and paſtimes, for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying of thy ſelf wherein, no iourney is too long, too tedious or chargeable, whereby you ſhew your want of Loue, by your little reioycing in the trueth, trauai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt it, not for it.</p>
            <p>Now let vs come to the laſt meanes to bee vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> men, and that is Magiſtracie, what anſwere will this giue? I doubt as the former. Let vs ſee a litle by more particular diſcourſe: Firſt, you Gentlemen to whom is committed the Sword in the Countrey, doe you vſe it to forward pietie and godlineſſſe there? Let the Greene meetings, the May-powles and May-fooles, the Wakes, Barebaitings, and Footeball play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings vpon the Sabbath day, ſay whether you doe or
<pb facs="tcp:4334:29"/> not; But to leaue you, let me come to this Citie, and to you (Right Honourable) the L. Mayor, with the reſt of your Brethren the Aldermen, and the Officers of this Corporation: Doe you exerciſe your Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to further Religion? Let the prophanation of the Sabbath, by trauailers into, and out of your Citie, the carying of burdens in your Citie: The publike and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Markets kept in your Citie, both in Streetes in Cheapeſide, and other places, by Apple-women, &amp;c. Gracious-ſtreete (I had almoſt ſaid Graceleſſe ſtreete) with her Morning and Euening Market: In Shops in the Morning, in Tipling-houſes, ware-houſes, whore-houſes and Tauernes all the day, witneſſe this, and more then this: The ſelling of corrupt Wares, yea, of the badges of Idolatrie, ſay what you doe; O belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, what ſhall I ſay? But mourne for theſe things. O draw out your Sword of Iuſtice (Right Honourable) and ſtand out like a man of Warre, for the redreſſe of theſe things: Know that your Authoritie is not onely for man, but for God, to maintaine his Lawes, knowe that you ſtand charged with the whole Citie, and the Gates of the ſame for the yeere, and therefore looke to it, you are guiltie of the ſinnes of thoſe that breake the Sabbath within your iuriſdiction, by any of the wayes aforeſaid, if you ſtriue and labour not the amendment of the ſame. You will ſay, what ſhall I doe? I will tell thee what, Set a man at euery Gate of the Citie, and let the Gates be ſhut before the Sabbath, and not ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vntill the Sabbath bee ended, as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did, whom thou art herein to follow, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.19. and if this will not ſerue, vſe thy Authoritie to driue them
<pb facs="tcp:4334:29"/> from about the Gates, ſuffer not burdens to be caried, both vpon Carts, Horſes, and the backes of men, as they vſually are, the Lord cannot endure it, <hi>Iere.</hi> 17.20 <hi>Ad finem.</hi> Let not the Sabbath be a Market day for the things of the body, which God hath ſet to be the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket day of the ſoule. Looke that Play bookes and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Sonnets, the meanes of corrupting yong minds, bee not countenanced neither in Printing nor ſelling, by you, much leſſe Popiſh bookes: but with the reſt, forget not to abandon the Reliques of Idolatrie, from Cheapeſide, I meane, Rings with Crucifixes vpon the ſame, vſually ſold there: Is it not a thing vncredible, that our King who lamenteth the whore of Rome, ſhould haue in his Kingdome: yea, in the chiefeſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his Kingdome, and the ſtatelieſt ſtreete of the ſame, the Badges of that Whore to bee ſolde: yea, which is more from thence to bee tranſported to Popiſh Countries, to furniſh them with the ſame: O looke to theſe, and other groſſe matters, &amp; ſet your ſelfe to a happy and ſpeedy reformation of the ſame; ſet vpon it, you ſhall not looſe your labour, you ſhall get you praiſe, both in heauen and earth: God will loue you, the Angels loue you, and men will praiſe you: I for my part will, and my Brethren ſucceeding me in this place, will giue you your due praiſe: wee will ſay, many Mayors haue done worthily, but you haue excelled them all, as may witneſſe the good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of the late Mayor, and his officers your Honors and your predeceſſors, giuen vnto him for the good he did in reforming, in ſome meaſure ſome of the abhominations aforeſaide, who began to build the Temple, I meane this happy reformation for you,
<pb facs="tcp:4334:30"/> but I know not how it is vnhappily all caſt in the duſt againe. Conſider this (right Honourable) and ſet to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the worke you haue let ſlacke. And not onely this, but conſider why the Lord hath called you to this place, not that you ſhould play your part like a Player vpon the Stage, or to ſtand for a Cipher, but that you ſhould ſhew your ſelfe a man: and why hath he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red theſe things to be vnreformed, but that you ſhould doe the ſame? Let me ſay to you, as <hi>Mordecay</hi> to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster,</hi> Who knoweth whether God hath brought you to this place for this end, yea or no? Therefore doe it, if you will not, God will haue reformation by ſome <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> other, but you and yours ſhall periſh. If this will not perſwade, conſider a third thing, and that is the benefit that is likely to come hereby, and that not onely to you, but to this whole Citie, as the Prophet witneſſeth in Ierem. 17.24.25. And aſſure your ſelfe, if you doe it not, the neglect of this by you, will bring ſeuen worſe plagues, then yet haue beene ſeene in this Citie, that you ſhall be farre from ſitting, as now you doe with mirth, in your ſeates of command: O let this perſwade, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> or if not, hearken to a fourth perſwaſion: the comfort thou ſhalt haue in thy conſcience vpon thy death-bed if thou canſt turne thy ſelfe to the wall, and ſay, Lord behold I haue vvalked vvith an vpright heart in my Mayraltie: If thou canſt not ſay this, what wil it auaile thee, to make a Will, and to bequeath hundreds and thouſands, and yet art not able to turne thy ſelfe in peace to God? O conſider this, and as thou tendereſt the peace and comfort of conſcience, then, when all <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> things elſe will be comfortleſſe; ſo looke to diſcharge this I giue thee to vnderſtand of. If this will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile,
<pb facs="tcp:4334:30"/> let this laſt conſideration: the walking in thy of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, as I haue directed, will make thee with boldneſſe to appeare before God in prayer with <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> 5, 19. <hi>Remember me O my God in goodneſſe, according to all that I haue done for this people:</hi> Which he could neuer haue ſo boldly vttered as he did, except he had wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked conſcionably in his calling.</p>
            <p>O let theſe enter into your honourable breſt, and conſider of them at home and euery day, that we may ſee, to the praiſe of God and your ſaluation, ſome good effect of this daies worke. But why ſhould I ſtand ſo long vpon theſe things, me thinks I perceiue that you are and will be as ready to reforme theſe things, as I to diſcouer them, Deceaue not my perſwaſion (right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable) leaſt you fruſtrate your owne ſaluation. Thus hauing done with the fiue ſeuerall meanes, which euery man that reioyceth in the trueth, for the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the ſame in the place where he dwelleth, vſeth amongſt men, as they concerne him: let vs come to the means euery man that reioyceth in the truth, vſeth to further it by, with God, and that is prayer. Which fewe vſe, and therefore doe ſo little good as they doe, they thinke if they beſtow their liuings well, ſpeake for, and countenance good men, ſpende their money for furthering ſuch cauſes and perſons, and iourney to the ſame end, and vſe their Magiſtracie &amp; Authoritie for the like, then they haue done enough: but alas, there is one thing, which procureth a bleſſing to all theſe, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: and that is harty prayer, which <hi>Dauid</hi> vſed in the 51. <hi>Pſal. ver.</hi> 18. Be fauourable vnto Sion, for thy good pleaſure build vp the walls of Ieruſalem, without this, thinking his not ceaſing to giue the temples of his
<pb facs="tcp:4334:31"/> head any reſt, till he had found a place for the worſhip of God, and his great a-doe to procure the wealth of Ieruſalem, was to no end or little worth: See and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thy ſelfe, whether with the former thou ioine the latter, if not, it argueth thou haſt no great heart-bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to, or liking of Religion. Now followeth the third marke, whereby wee may know if wee reioyce in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Religion, and the happy ſucceſſe of the ſame, namely, If ſuch be companions to vs, and wee delight to haue our houſes fraughted with ſuch, both children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and the more forwarder that way the better li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of vs, nay if we be as we ſhould, wee will remoue from the Idols of <hi>Ieroboam</hi> and goe to <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> wee will not ſtay in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court, but will goe to liue with Gods children, though in affliction: But alas where is this to be found, that the companie of ſuch are acceptable to vs? and ſo conſequently, where is there any reioycing in the trueth? this proueth, that fewe or none bee louers of the ſame. I doubt the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> fourth will haue little better ſucceſſe, which is a mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for the decay of Religion, but where is there any to be found, that is grieued for the carying away of the Arke by the Philiſtims? crying with <hi>Elies</hi> daughter in law, <hi>the Arke is taken away and the glory is departed from Iſrael.</hi> Where is any to be found ſorrowing, to ſee the people ſcattered as ſheepe vpon a mountain without a ſhepheard? who cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth this amongſt, nay, the greateſt of their griefes and ſorrowes? that the wayes to Gods houſe are vntroden, &amp; that her enemies are the chiefe therein? but who of all men doth make the abſence from Gods houſe and ſeruice, and the exerciſes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the matter of their complaint, not being any
<pb facs="tcp:4334:31"/> where, whilſt they are abſent there-from, able to ſing merrily? Few ſuch (beloued) if any, therefore fewe, if any, reioycing to ſee Religion flouriſh. As there bee few that mourne for the abſence of it, ſo who will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the ſame? which is the fifth marke of a man reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing in the trueth, and that both by ſpeaking for it, as <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> giuing a reaſon of it to the aduerſaries, ſuffering for it as the Apoſtles &amp; Chriſtians formerly, and in Queene <hi>Mary</hi> her daies: and laſtly, practiſing the ſame. Many will doe the former, and happily the latter, but fewe endure to do the ſecond: <hi>Ergo,</hi> few reioyce in the truth. And as few will defend it in this manner, who is there that prefer it to their chiefe ioy? which is the ſixt and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> laſt marke, whereby wee may knowe whether wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in the trueth, yea or no: who count all things dung in compariſon of that? who is there that prefer it to their life? with <hi>Paul Acts,</hi> 20. <hi>My life is not deare vnto me, ſo I may finiſh my courſe with ioy?</hi> or with Nehe. 6.11. <hi>Should ſuch a man as I flee, who is he being as I am, that would goe into the temple to liue, I will not goe in. Or with Hester, if I periſh, I periſh:</hi> Alas few ſuch, life is ſweet will all ſay, but I ſay to a Chriſtian man and woman. <hi>Religion</hi> the life of the ſoule is farre ſweeter. Thus haue we examined from top to toe, both by <hi>Quid charitas abstinet,</hi> and <hi>quid efficit,</hi> and few doe we finde to haue loue dwelling in them, becauſe few loue righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or honeſt dealing with men, or Religion towards God. I will onely lay downe two motiues to moue the latter to be in loue with Religion, and to reioyce in the ſame, and ſo I will ceaſe. Which are theſe. 1. The neceſſitie of it, without it there is no comming to the Kingdome of heauen, for we muſt reioyce to ſee Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:4334:32"/> raigne here by grace in the hearts of men, elſe we ſhall neuer come to reioyce with him in glory.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> To be louers and makers much of Religion, and the true feare of God is the way to true honour here, and euerlaſting honour in the life to come. For the firſt, that part of the commination to olde <hi>Ely,</hi> plainely ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth: he that honoureth me, ſhall be honoured, but he that deſpiſeth me ſhall be deſpiſed. Which experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſheweth, for who is ſo truely feared and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced both at home and abroad, of his owne and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as he that truely feareth the Lord? Much is the complaining of men in theſe dayes, that they neuer had ſuch ſturdy ſeruants, and no man ſuch diſobedient children? alas they enter not into the true conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe things, if they did, they ſhould finde it as a iuſt iudgement of God vpon them, for their want of feare and loue to his, therefore hee maketh them that ſhould moſt reuerence thee, to be thy greateſt griefe &amp; heart-breaking: for what was the cauſe that ſtrangers ſhrunke away, and did feare in their priuy chambers at the preſence of <hi>Dauid?</hi> becauſe he kept the waies of the Lord, &amp; did not wickedly againſt his God. And what was the cauſe, that the yong men hid themſelues when they ſaw <hi>Iob,</hi> &amp; the aged aroſe and ſtood vp? becauſe he was a righteous man, feete to the lame, and eies to the blind, ſo that it is euer true, and euer ſhall be, that the way truly to be reuerenced, is to bee truly religious, which wee ſhall finde further to be true, both in their life and death, for proofe whereof, that example of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoiada</hi> is worth alwaies remembrance, who ſetting himſelf wholy to reſtore religion &amp; the true ſeruice of God, and to abandon Idolatry, was therfore honoured
<pb facs="tcp:4334:32"/> both in life &amp; death: in life God honoured him in his mariage, for he was ſon in law to one King, &amp; brother in law to another, 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 22. <hi>penult,</hi> and more then that King <hi>Ioaſh</hi> would do nothing without his counſell and aduiſe: and in his death was he no leſſe honored then in his life, companion he was to Kings in his life, &amp; ſo in his death, 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 24. they buried him in the City of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> with the Kings, becauſe he had done good in Iſrael, and towards God &amp; his houſe. Which truth will the better appeare, if we conſider how God hath diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the enemies of his Church, by bringing vpon them ſhamefull deaths, as witnes <hi>Haman, Achitophell</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> who for eaſe went and hanged themſelues. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> with his lowſie death, <hi>Zenacherib</hi> ſlaine with the fruite of his owne bowels, whilſt he was worſhipping <hi>Niſroch</hi> his God, 2. Chron. 32.21. and <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> 2. Chron. 24 25. who was ouercome with a fewe, left in great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, killed by his own ſeruants, and not graced with buriall in the Sepulchres of the Kings, and all for his falling from the truth, and miſuſing of <hi>Zechariah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iehoiada.</hi> No better, but farre worſe was the end of <hi>Zedekiah</hi> for murdering <hi>Vriah,</hi> and ſhewing his diſlike to the truth of God, as it plainely appeareth by comparing Ier. 22.18.19. vvith Ier. 26.22.23. Hee vvas buried without mourners, as a man whoſe death all wiſhed, and were glad of: they lamented him not, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Ah my brother, or Ah my ſiſter, neither did they mourne for him, ſaying, Ah Lord, and Ah his glory: he was buried as an Aſſe is buried, euen drawne and caſt forth without the gates of Ieruſalem: thus hath God ſhewed diſhonour vppon them that haue diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him. Let this goe to your hearts, and preuaile with
<pb facs="tcp:4334:33"/> you, to encreaſe your loue by reioycing in the truth of God, and to ſee Religion flouriſh.</p>
            <p>To this I know ſome of you will obiect, that you haue knowne men, who haue beene farre from this I ſpeake of, and yet haue died as quietly, beene buried as honourably, and reſpected, reuerenced, and honoured as much in their liues, as any that haue beene, or are ſo too too much religious. Vnto which I anſwer, how knoweſt thou, they haue died ſo quietly, thou knoweſt not what hearts they haue, a faire outſide thou ſeeſt, but the horror and diſquietnes of his ſoule is hid from thee, he is loath and aſhamed to let it be ſeene, and the Diuell not willing thou ſhouldeſt beholde the ſame, leaſt it ſhould fright thee, and thou auoid his manner of liuing, leaſt thou ſhouldeſt come to the ſame end: his buriall is no other but that which is common to the wicked: yea the wicked haue moſt of that pompe, not one heart mourning for him, but many blacke mockers rather then mourners: His honour, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and reſpect he hath, is not true &amp; worthy, from the heart, but ſeruile, becauſe they dare doe no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, thoſe whom thou ſpeakeſt of being like the great Maſtiues, whom the litle Curs dare not but crouch to, leaſt the Maſtiues ſhould all to rend them. Thus thou ſeeſt all they haue, is but ſo in ſhew, not in deede, labor thou then to follow Chriſt, to loue religion from thy heart, that honour and true dignity may bee heaped vpon thee heere, and euerlaſting honour in the life to come. Which God for his Chriſts ſake graunt vnto vs all. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4334:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
